<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<strings>
    <!-- INSPIRE metadata rules translation / START -->
    <M35>[INSPIRE] - Title is mandatory</M35>
    <M36>[INSPIRE] - Abstract is mandatory</M36>
    <M37>[INSPIRE] - Resource type is mandatory</M37>
    <M38>[INSPIRE] - Unique resource identifier is mandatory</M38>
    <M39>[INSPIRE] - ISO topic category is mandatory</M39>
    <M40>[INSPIRE] - Keyword is mandatory</M40>
    <M41>[INSPIRE] - Geographic bounding box is mandatory</M41>
    <M42>[INSPIRE] - Temporal reference is mandatory</M42>
    <M43>[INSPIRE] - Lineage is mandatory</M43>
    <M44>[INSPIRE] - Conformity is mandatory (in DQ_DomainConsistency.result.DQ_ConformanceResult)</M44>
    <M45>[INSPIRE] - Conditions for access and use is mandatory</M45>
    <M46>[INSPIRE] - Limitations on public access is mandatory</M46>
    <M47>[INSPIRE] - Responsible organisation is mandatory</M47>
    <M48>[INSPIRE] - Metadata point of contact is mandatory</M48>
    <M49>[INSPIRE] - Metadata language is mandatory</M49>
    <M50>[INSPIRE] - Metadata date is mandatory</M50>
    <M51>[INSPIRE] (service) - Coupled resource is mandatory if linkage to data sets on which the service operates are available</M51>
    <M52>[INSPIRE] - Resource locator is mandatory if linkage is available</M52>
    <M53>[INSPIRE] - There may be zero or one condition applying to access and use</M53>
    <M54>[INSPIRE] - The value of accessConstraints is otherRestrictions, if and only if they are instances of otherConstraints expressing limitations on public access</M54>
    <M55>[INSPIRE] (data sets and series) - Resource language is mandatory if the resource includes textual information</M55>
    <M56>[INSPIRE] - Spatial resolution is mandatory if an equivalent scale or a resolution distance can be specified</M56>
    <M57>[ISO19119 for services] - OperationName is mandatory</M57>
    <M58>[ISO19119 for services] - DCP is mandatory</M58>
    <M59>[ISO19119 for services] - ConnectPoint is mandatory</M59>
    <M60>[ISO19119 for services] - ServiceType is mandatory</M60>
    
    <alert.M35><div><h2>INSPIRE - Title is mandatory</h2></div></alert.M35>
    <alert.M36><div><h2>INSPIRE - Abstract is mandatory</h2>
        <br/>
        <b>Example:</b><br/>
        Dataset contains large scale (1:1.000) topography, which covers the whole country.
    </div></alert.M36>
    <alert.M37><div><h2>INSPIRE - Resource type is mandatory</h2>
        <br/>
        <b>Implementing instructions:</b><br/>
        The values of MD_ScopeCode in the scope of the
        directive (See SC4 in 1.2) are:
        <ul>
            <li>dataset for spatial datasets;</li>
            <li>series for spatial dataset series;</li>
            <li>services for spatial data services.</li>
        </ul> 
        The hierarchyLevel property is not mandated by ISO
        19115, but is mandated for conformance to the INSPIRE
        Metadata Implementing rules (See SC2 in 1.2).        
    </div></alert.M37>
    <alert.M38><div><h2>INSPIRE - Unique resource identifier is mandatory</h2>
        <br/>
        <b>Implementing instructions</b><br/>        
        Mandatory for dataset and dataset series.<br/>
        <b>Example:</b> 527c4cac-070c-4bca-9aaf-92bece7be902
    </div></alert.M38>
    <alert.M39><div><h2>INSPIRE - ISO topic category is mandatory</h2><br/>
        The topic categories defined in Part D 2 of the INSPIRE
        Implementing rules for metadata are derived directly from
        the topic categories defined in B.5.27 of ISO 19115.
        INSPIRE Implementing rules for metadata define the
        INSPIRE data themes to which each topic category is
        Implementing instructions applicable, i.e., Administrative units (I.4) and Statistical
        units (III.1) are INSPIRE themes for which the
        boundaries topic category is applicable. The value of the
        ISO 19115/ISO 19119 metadata element is the value
        appearing in the “name” column of the table in B.5.27 of
        ISO 19115.
    </div></alert.M39>
    <alert.M40><div><h2>INSPIRE - Keyword is mandatory</h2></div></alert.M40>
    <alert.M41><div><h2>INSPIRE - Geographic bounding box is mandatory</h2><br/>
        <ul>
            <li>
                Mandatory for spatial dataset and dataset series.                
            </li>
            <li>
                Conditional for spatial services: Mandatory for services with
                an explicit geographic extent                
            </li>
        </ul>
        
        <b>Implementing instructions</b>
        <ul>
            <li>
                There are as many bounding boxes defining the geographic
                location of the resource as instances of
                identificationInfo[1]/*/extent/*/geographicElement having the
                westBoundLongitude, eastBoundLongitude,
                southBoundLatitude and northBoundLatitude properties. The
                four coordinates of the bounding box originate from the same
                instance.                
            </li>
            <li>
                The bounding box shall be as small as possible.      
            </li>
            <li>
                If the bounding box crosses the 180 meridian, then the value
                of the westBoundLongitude will be greater than the
                eastBoundLongitude value.      
            </li>
            <li>
                The coordinates of the bounding box are expressed in any
                geographic coordinate reference system with a Greenwich
                Prime Meridian (See SC13 in 1.2).   
            </li>
        </ul>      
        
    </div></alert.M41>
    <alert.M42><div><h2>INSPIRE - Temporal reference is mandatory</h2>
        <b>Implementing instructions</b><br/>
        Each instance of the temporal extent may be an interval
        of dates or an individual date. The overall time period
        covered by the content of the resource may be
        composed of one or many instances.<br/>
        Or a reference date of the cited resource (publication, last revision or creation).
        <br/>
        <b>Example:</b>
        From 1977-03-10T11:45:30 to 2005-01-15T09:10:00
    </div></alert.M42>
    <alert.M43><div><h2>INSPIRE - Lineage is mandatory</h2><br/>
        <ul>
            <li>Mandatory for spatial dataset and spatial dataset series.</li>
            <li>Not applicable to services.</li>
        </ul>
        In addition to general explanation of the data producer’s knowledge
        about the lineage of a dataset it is possible to put data quality
        statements here.<br/>
        A single ISO 19115 metadata set may comprise more than one set of
        Implementing instructions   quality information, each of them having one or zero lineage
        statement. There shall be one and only one set of quality information
        scoped to the full resource and having a lineage statement (See
        SC6 in 1.2).<br/>
        <b>Example:</b>    Dataset has been digitised from the standard 1:5.000 map
        
    </div></alert.M43>
    <alert.M44><div><h2>INSPIRE - Conformity is mandatory (in DQ_DomainConsistency.result.DQ_ConformanceResult)</h2><br/>
        <b>Implementing instructions</b> <br/>
        The first two degrees of conformity defined in Part D 5 of
        the INSPIRE Implementing rules for metadata map to two
        values of the Boolean domain of ISO 19115. The last value
        corresponds to the case where no conformance statement
        is expressed in the metadata for the related specification.<br/>
        
        <b>Example:</b> title “INSPIRE Implementing rules laying down
        technical arrangements for the interoperability and
        harmonisation of administrative boundaries”.
                
    </div></alert.M44>
    <alert.M45><div><h2>INSPIRE - Conditions for access and use is mandatory</h2><br/>
    </div></alert.M45>
    <alert.M46><div><h2>INSPIRE - Limitations on public access is mandatory</h2></div></alert.M46>
    <alert.M47><div><h2>INSPIRE - Responsible organisation for the resource is mandatory</h2><br/>
        Relative to a responsible organisation, but there may be
        many responsible organisations for a single resource.
        <br/>
        See identification section / point of contact.
    </div></alert.M47>
    <alert.M48><div><h2>INSPIRE - Metadata point of contact is mandatory</h2><br/>
        <b>Implementing instructions:</b><br/>
        The role of the responsible party serving as a metadata
        point of contact is out of scope of the INSPIRE
        Implementing Rules, but this property is mandated by ISO
        19115. Its value can be defaulted to pointOfContact.<br/>
        See metadata section.
    </div></alert.M48>
    <alert.M49><div><h2>INSPIRE - Metadata language is mandatory</h2><br/>
        The language property is not mandated by ISO 19115, but
        is mandated for conformance to the INSPIRE Metadata
        Implementing rules
    </div></alert.M49>
    <alert.M50><div><h2>INSPIRE - Metadata date is mandatory</h2></div></alert.M50>
    <alert.M51><div><h2>INSPIRE (service) - Coupled resource is mandatory if linkage to data sets on which the service operates are available</h2>
        <br/>
        <b>Implementing instructions</b><br/>
        Not applicable to dataset and dataset series<br/>
        Conditional to services: Mandatory if linkage to datasets on which the service operates are available.<br/>
        
        <ul>
            <li>The property shall be implemented by reference (See
        SC11 in 1.2) and the MD_DataIdentification object
        reference value is the code of the Coupled resource
        metadata element.</li>
            <li>For consistency, the code of the Couple resource
        metadata element should also be the code of one of
        the Unique resource identifiers of the corresponding
        coupled resource.</li>
        </ul>
    </div></alert.M51>
    <alert.M52><div><h2>INSPIRE - Resource locator is mandatory if linkage is available</h2><br/>
        See advanved view / distribution section / only resource element.
        <br/>
        <b>Implementing instructions:</b><br/>
            <ul>
                <li>Specify a valid URL to the resource. If no direct link to
            a resource is available, provide link to a contact point
            where more information about the resource is
            available.</li>
                <li>For a service, the Resource Locator might be one of
                the following:</li>
                <ul>
                    <li>A link to the service capabilities document;</li>
                    <li>A link to the service WSDL document (SOAP Binding);</li>
                    <li>A link to a web page with further instructions</li>
                    <li>A link to a client application that directly accesses the service</li>
                </ul>
            </ul>
            
    </div></alert.M52>
    <alert.M53><div><h2>INSPIRE - There may be zero or one condition applying to access and use</h2><br/>
        Access constraints applied to assure the protection of
        privacy or intellectual property, and any special restrictions
        or limitations on obtaining the resource.<br/>
        <b>Example:</b> intellectualPropertyRights (rights to financial benefit from
        and control of distribution of non-tangible property that is a
        result of creativity).
        <br/>
        Classification:
        <b>Example:</b> restricted (not for general disclosure)
        <br/>
        Use limitation:
        <b>Example:</b> not to be used for navigation
        <br/>
    </div></alert.M53>
    <alert.M54><div><h2>INSPIRE - The value of accessConstraints is otherRestrictions, if and only if they are instances of otherConstraints expressing limitations on public access</h2></div></alert.M54>
    <alert.M55><div><h2>INSPIRE (datasets and series) - Resource language is mandatory if the resource includes textual information</h2><br/>
        An instance of the language property is mandated by ISO
        19115 ; it can be defaulted to the value of the Metadata
        Implementing instructions Language when the dataset or the dataset series does not
        contain textual information.
        <br/>
        <b>Implementing instructions:</b><br/>
        Codelist (See ISO/TS 19139) based on alpha-3 codes of
        ISO 639-2.
    </div></alert.M55>
    <alert.M56><div><h2>INSPIRE - Spatial resolution is mandatory if an equivalent scale or a resolution distance can be specified</h2><br/>
        <b>Implementing instructions:</b>
        <ul>
            <li>
                Each spatial resolution is either an equivalent scale OR a ground
                sample distance.                
            </li>
            <li>
                When two equivalent scales or two ground sample distances are
                expressed, the spatial resolution is an interval bounded by these two
                values.                
            </li>
        </ul>
        <b>Example:</b> 5000 (e.g. 1:5000 scale map)
    </div></alert.M56>
    <alert.M57><div><h2>[ISO19119 for services] - OperationName is mandatory</h2></div></alert.M57>
    <alert.M58><div><h2>[ISO19119 for services] - DCP is mandatory</h2></div></alert.M58>
    <alert.M59><div><h2>[ISO19119 for services] - ConnectPoint is mandatory</h2></div></alert.M59>
    <alert.M60><div><h2>[ISO19119 for services] - ServiceType is mandatory</h2><br/>
        Mandatory for services.<br/>
        Not applicable to dataset and dataset series<br/>
        <b>Example:</b> OGC:CSW
        
    </div></alert.M60>
    <!-- INSPIRE metadata rules translation / END -->
</strings>