<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
    <chapter id="gast">
        <title>GeoNetwork’s Administrator Survival Tool - GAST</title>
        <section>
            <title>What is GAST?</title>
            <para>GAST stands for <literal>GeoNetwork’s Administrator Survival Tool</literal> and is a standalone
                application whose purpose is to simplify some low level tasks like change of the
                servlet, configuration of the JDBC account, setup the database and so on. Most
                of the GAST’s facilities work only for the GeoNetwork’s installation where GAST
                is in. This implies that if you are using a servlet container other than Jetty
                (like Tomcat) you will not be able to change some options (like the servlet’s
                name). Other facilities work for any servlet container but you have to specify
                the GeoNetwork’s URL into the GAST’s configuration dialog.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Starting GAST</title>
            <para>GAST belongs to the core components so it is installed by default.</para>
            <para>On Windows computers, simply select the <literal>Start GAST</literal> option under the 
                GeoNetwork opensource program group under <literal>Start > Programs > GeoNetwork opensource</literal></para>
            <para>Other options to start GAST are either to use a java command <emphasis 
                role="bold">from a terminal window</emphasis>
                or just click its jar’s icon. To issue the java command you have to:</para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>change directory to the GeoNetwork installation folder</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>issue the command <code>java -jar gast/gast.jar</code></para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            
            <para>You can also try to simply open the GeoNetwork installation folder, go to the
                gast folder and doubleclick on the gast.jar file. If you have Java installed, GAST should
                start in a few seconds.</para>
            <para>To run, GAST requires Java 1.5. It will not work on Java 1.4 and it
                should run on Java 1.6 (this has not been tested!).</para>
            
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Operating modes</title>
            <para>When you start GAST, you get an application window like the one in <xref linkend="admin_gast"/>.
                On the left side you have a panel with the tools you can use. After selecting a
                tool, on the right side you get the tool’s options panel.</para>
            
            <figure id="admin_gast">
                <title>
                    GAST’s main window with a tool selected
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/admin/gast-main.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            
            <para>Every function has an operating mode, which defines the condition under which
                the tool can be used. The tool’s mode is shown with an icon on the right side of
                the tool’s name. The operating modes, with their icons are summarized in the
                following table:</para>
            
            
            <informaltable frame="all" id="gast_operating_modes">
                <tgroup cols="3">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="c1" colwidth="3cm" align="left"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="c2" colwidth="2cm" align="center"/>
                    <colspec colnum="3" colname="c3" colwidth="10cm" align="left"/>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Mode</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Icon</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Description</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Restarted</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>
                                    <inlinemediaobject>
                                        <imageobject>
                                            <imagedata fileref="images/icons/reload.png"/>
                                        </imageobject>
                                    </inlinemediaobject>
                               </para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>The tool can be always used, but GeoNetwork must be
                                    restarted in order to make the change effective.</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Running</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>
                                    <inlinemediaobject>
                                        <imageobject>
                                            <imagedata fileref="images/icons/launch.png"/>
                                        </imageobject>
                                    </inlinemediaobject>
                               </para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>The tool can be used only if GeoNetwork is running.
                               </para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Stopped</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>
                                    <inlinemediaobject>
                                        <imageobject>
                                            <imagedata fileref="images/icons/stop.png"/>
                                        </imageobject>
                                    </inlinemediaobject>
                               </para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>The tool can be used only if GeoNetwork is stopped. This
                                    is important because some tools change the database’s
                                    account or create the database from scratch. These are
                                    sensitive operations that cannot be performed while
                                    GeoNetwork is running.</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Tools subdivision</title>
            <para>All GAST tools present into the left panel are logically subdivided into
                groups. Each group represents a GeoNetwork’s aspect for which GAST allows you a
                graphic interface. The groups are:</para>
            <para>Configuration You can change some configuration parameters, like the servlet’s
                name, JDBC account etc... Management General purpose tools related to the site’s
                administration. Database Operations that regard the database. Here you can find
                tools to create a database from scratch, creating the schema and filling it with
                proper data. Migration Tools that allow you to migrate metadata from old
                installation.</para>
            
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Server and Account configuration dialog</title>
            <para>Some of the GAST’s tools access a running GeoNetwork application. Usually, GAST connects
                to GeoNetwork using the connection parameters it finds on the installation
                folder but you can specify other parameters in order to connect to other
                instances. This is required when the GeoNetwork instance is not running on the
                embedded Jetty server. In addition to that, some tools require authentication so
                account parameters must be provided.</para>
            <para>To provide these parameters, you have to use the GAST ’s configuration dialog.
                To open the dialog, select <literal>Options >> Config</literal> from the menubar. You will
                get the dialog shown in <xref linkend="admin_gast_config"/>.</para>
            
            <figure id="admin_gast_config" >
                <title>
                    The configuration dialog
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/admin/gast-options.png" width="7cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            
            <para>The dialog is subdivided into 2 areas: Server Tells GAST how to connect to a
                running GeoNetwork. If you select the embedded option, GAST will get the
                connection parameters from the installation directory. Alternatively, if you use
                Tomcat or an external servlet container you have to choose the external option
                and provide the connection parameters yourself. Remember that this will work
                only for tools which operating mode is <emphasis>Running</emphasis>. For all the
                others, GAST will access the parameters from the installation directory. Account
                Some tools require authentication. To authenticate, simply select the Use this
                account option and provide the username and password of a valid account. These
                parameters will work for both the embedded instance and for any external
                instance.</para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>