<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
    <chapter id="thesaurus">
        <title>Thesaurus</title>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <para>Thesaurus support in GeoNetwork allows:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Metadata editing</emphasis>: controled vocabulary on the metadata editing interface
                        for ISO and Dublin Core</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Administration interface</emphasis> allows import/export/creation/browse
                    thesaurus</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Search interface</emphasis>: a list of keyword is proposed for the keyword
                    criteria</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>On a node, thesaurus types could be defined as:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>External</emphasis>: When a thesaurus is imported, it is flagged to ”external” which
                        means that users are not allowed to edit the thesaurus. This thesaurus is
                        managed by an external organisation.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>Local</emphasis>: When a thesaurus is created, it is flagged to ”local” which means
                        that users are allowed to edit the thesaurus.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Thesaurus / SKOS format</title>
            <para>The Simple Knowledge Organisation Systems (SKOS)
                    <literal>http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/</literal> is an area of work developing
                specifications and standards to support the use of knowledge organisation systems
                (KOS) such as thesauri, classification schemes. This format is used by GeoNetwork to
                store thesaurus information.</para>
            <para>A concept is defined by an identifier, a prefered label, a definition and links
                with other concepts. Labels and definitions could be stored in multiple languages
                (using the xml:lang attributes). Three type of links between concepts have been
                defined in the SKOS format:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>related terms</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>broader terms</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>narrower terms</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>For example, a concept ”ABLETTE” could be defined as follow with a label in french
                and english, linked to broader concept:</para>
<programlisting><?db-font-size 75% ?><![CDATA[
<skos:Concept rdf:about="http://www.oieau.org/concept#c4fc54576dc00227b82a709287ac3681">
    <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="fr">ABLETTE</skos:prefLabel> 
    <skos:prefLabel xml:lang="en">BLEAK</skos:prefLabel>
    <skos:broader rdf:resource="http://www.oieau.org/concept#9f25ece36d04776e09492c66627cccb9"/> 
</skos:Concept>]]></programlisting>
            <para>GeoNetwork support multilingual thesaurus (e.g. Agrovoc). Search and edition are
                made based on current user interface language (i.e. if the interface is in english,
                when editing metadata, GeoNetwork will only search for concept in english).</para>

        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Thesaurus administration</title>
            <para>To reach the thesaurus administration page you have to be logged in as an
                administrator. From the administration page, click the link ”Manage thesaurii”.
                Figure 5.3 shows the list of thesaurus available in the GeoNetwork node. The page
                shows a list of thesaurus that have been created or imported. The upper part of the
                page allows user to edit/add/modify/consult thesaurus. The lower part allows upload
                of thesaurus in SKOS format.</para>

            <section>
                <title>Creation of a new thesaurus</title>
                <para>To create a new thesaurus, click the ”+” sign in the category you want your
                    thesaurus to be in. Once created, the thesaurus could be updated through the
                    edit interface. The meaning of each column is as follows:</para>
                <para>Type The type allows to classify thesaurus according to its type. First, is
                    defined the type of the thesaurus following ISO category list, then the type
                    indicates if the thesaurus is a local one or an external one. Name This is the
                    thesaurus’s name provided by the administrator on creation or filename on
                    upload. When creating a thesaurus, the name of the thesaurus will be the
                    filename of the thesaurus.</para>

                <figure id="admin_thesaurus_admin">
                    <title>Administration interface for thesaurus</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/thesaurus/thesaurus-Admin.png" width="13cm" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>For each thesaurus the following buttons are available:</para>
                <para>Download Link to the rdf file. Delete Remove thesaurus from the current node.
                    View If type is external, the view button allows to search and view concepts.
                    Edit If type is local, the edit button allows to search, add, remove and view
                    concepts.</para>

            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Import existing thesaurus</title>
                <para>GeoNetwork allows thesaurus import in SKOS format. Once uploaded, an external
                    thesaurus could not be updated. Select the category, browse for the thesaurus
                    file and click upload. The file is located in
                        <literal>/web/xml/codelist/external/thesauri/category/</literal>.</para>

                <figure id="admin_thesaurus_upload">
                    <title>Upload interface for thesaurus</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/thesaurus/thesaurus-upload.png" width="13cm" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>At the bottom of the page there are the following buttons:</para>
                <para>Back Go back to the main administration page. Upload Upload the selected rdf
                    file to the node. Then it will list all thesaurus available on the node.</para>

            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Editing/browsing thesaurus: add/remove/browse keywords</title>
            <para>From the thesaurus administration interface, click on the edit button for a local
                thesaurus or the view button for an external thesaurus. This interface allows:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>keywords search</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>add/remove keywords for local thesaurus.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>Use the textbox and the type of search in order to search for keywords.</para>

            <figure id="admin_thesaurus_browse">
                <title>Browse interface for thesaurus</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/thesaurus/thesaurus-KeywordSearch.png" width="12cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <figure id="admin_thesaurus_keyword">
                <title>Keyword description</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/thesaurus/thesaurus-KeywordDesc.png" width="12cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Metadata editing: adding keywords</title>
            <para>When editing metadata in ISO or Dublin core, the keyword fields autocomplete when
                editor fill the fields. Keywords available in all thesaurus know by the current node
                are returned. Editor could select one of the list or could type any other keywords.</para>

            <figure id="admin_thesaurus_keyword_edit">
                <title>Autocomplete in keywords editor</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/thesaurus/thesaurus-EditKeywords.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Search criteria: keywords</title>
            <para>In the advanced search interface, the keyword field will proposed all keywords
                used in the metadata. These keywords are indexed by Lucene on creation/update of
                metadata. The number of metadata linked to all keywords available in the index are
                display. User could type in the keyword field or click the icon to get the list of
                keywords available.</para>

            <figure id="admin_thesaurus_search">
                <title>Thesaurus search interface</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/thesaurus/thesaurus-SearchInterface.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <figure id="admin_thesaurus_search_auto">
                <title>Autocomplete function in thesaurus search interface</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/thesaurus/thesaurus-SearchKeywordAutocomp.png" width="7cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
