<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
    <chapter id="metadata_ownership">
        <title>Metadata ownership</title>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <para>Starting from release 2.1.0, GeoNetwork has a new metadata access policy. The
                old edit and admin privileges have been removed and the concept of reviewer has
                been introduced. The purpose of this new profile is to control when a metadata
                can be published outside or not. In previous releases, all users belonging to a
                group with edit privileges could edit the same metadata. Now, a metadata is only
                visible to its creator, to a reviewer which has access to the group owner and to
                an administrator.</para>
            
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Access policy</title>
            
            <para>A public metadata is a metadata that has the view privilege for the group
                named all.</para>
            <section>
                <title>Visualization</title>
                <para>An administrator can view any metadata.</para>
                <para>A reviewer can view a metadata if:</para>
                
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The group owner is one of the groups assigned to the reviewer.
                       </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>He is the metadata owner.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>A user administrator or an editor can view:</para>
                
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>All metadata that have the view privilege in one of the groups
                            visible to them.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>All metadata created by theirself.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>A registered user can view:</para>
                
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>All metadata that have the view privilege in one of the groups
                            visible to them.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>Public metadata can be viewed by any user (logged in or not).</para>
                
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>Editing</title>
                <para>An administrator can edit any metadata.</para>
                <para>A reviewer can edit a metadata if:</para>
                
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The group owner is one of the groups assigned to the reviewer.
                       </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>He is the metadata owner.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>A user administrator or an editor can edit only metadata created by
                    theirself.</para>
                
            </section>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Privileges</title>
            <para>The privileges administration page is accessible only by:</para>
            
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>All administrators</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>All reviewers that have access to the metadata’s group owner.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The owner of the metadata</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>Regarding privileges for the all and intranet groups, only administrators and
                reviewers can edit them.</para>
            
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Ownership transfer</title>
            <para>A typical need that arises when a user is dismissed is to transfer all their
                metadata to another user into another group. To fill this need, the transfer
                ownership functionality has been introduced. This is located in the
                administration page (<xref linkend="admin_ownership_where"/>) and once selected, leads to the page shown
                in <xref linkend="admin_ownership_options"/>.</para>
            
			 <figure id="admin_ownership_where">
                <title>
                    How to reach the transfer ownership page
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/admin/web-ownership-where.png" width="11cm" align="center" />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>Initially, the page shows only a drop down for a Source editor. The drop down
                is filled with all GeoNetwork’s users which are editors and own some metadata.
                Selecting an editor means selecting all metadata that belong to that editor. An
                empty drop down means that there are no editors with metadata associated and
                hence no transfer is possible.</para>
            <para>Note The drop down will be filled with all editors visible to you. If you are
                not an administrator, you will view only a subset of all editors.</para>
            
             <figure id="admin_ownership_options">
                <title>
                    The transfer ownership page
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/admin/web-ownership-options.png" width="9cm" align="center" />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>Once a source editor has been selected, a set of rows is displayed. Each row
                refers to an editor’s group for which there are privileges. The meaning of each
                column is the following:</para>
            <para>Source group This is a group that has privileges in the metadata that belong
                to the source editor. Put in another way, if one of the editor’s metadata has
                privileges for one group, that group is listed here. Target group This is the
                destination group of the transfering process. All privileges relative to the
                source group are transferred to the target group. The target group drop down is
                filled with all groups visible to the logged user (tipically an administrator or
                a user administrator). By default, the source group is selected in the target
                drop down. Privileges to groups All and Intranet are not transferrable. Target
                editor Once a target group is selected, this drop down is filled with all
                editors that belong to that target group. Operation Actually only the Transfer
                operation is possible.</para>
            <para>By selecting the Transfer operation, if the source group is different than the
                target group, the system performs the ownership transfer, shows a brief summary
                and removes the current row because now there are no privileges to transfer
                anymore.</para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>