<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
    <chapter id="import_facilities">
        <title>Import facilities</title>
        <section>
            <title>Batch import</title>
            <para>The batch import facility allows you to import a set of metadata into the
                system all at once. In order to use this facility, you have to be logged in as
                an administrator. After the login step, go to the administration page and select
                the batch import’s link (<xref linkend="admin_batchimport_where"/>. The link is surrounded with a red
                rectangle). </para>

             <figure id="admin_batchimport_where">
                <title>
                    How to reach the batch import page
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/admin/web-batchimport-where.png" width="11cm" align="center" />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
                
            <para>Clicking the link, you will reach the batch import’s page as illustrated in
                <xref linkend="admin_batchimport_options"/>. You have to specify a set of parameters to make the import working.
                They are: </para>
            <para>Directory This is the full path on the server’s file system of the directory
                to scan. GeoNetwork will look for and try to import all XML files present into
                this directory. It is important to notice that this is the directory on the
                <emphasis>server</emphasis> machine and <emphasis>not</emphasis> on the
                client of the user that is doing the import. All metadata files present into the
                import directory <emphasis>must</emphasis> have the same schema format. Schema
                GeoNetwork supports only some metadata formats so you have to specify the schema
                of the metadata you want to import. If a metadata does not belong to the
                selected schema, the entire operation will be aborted. Validate This is a simple
                validation step that you can choose to perform. The metadata is validated
                against its schema. Group You have to select a group to associate to the
                imported metadata. Usually the group is the creator of the metadata set.
                Category You can specify one category to associate to your metadata in order to
                simplify the search. Stylesheet This is a powerfull option because allows you to
                specify a stylesheet for an XSL transformation. The drop down control is filled
                with files taken from the web/xsl/conversion/import folder : all XSL files you
                put there will be made available. This is a dymanic process so you don’t have to
                restart GeoNetwork. The purpose of this option is to allow the conversion of a
                metadata into a suitable format that is supported by GeoNetwork. Therefore, it
                is important that the result of the transformation matches the schema format
                selected above. </para>
            <para>Below the page, there are the following buttons: </para>
            <para>Back Goes back to the administration form. Upload Starts the import process.
                When the process ends, the total count of imported metadata will be shown.
                Please notice that the import is transactional: the metadata set will be fully
                imported or fully discarded (there are no partial imports). Files that starts
                with ’.’ or that do not end with ’.xml’ are ignored. </para>
            
             <figure id="admin_batchimport_options">
                <title>
                    The batch import options
                </title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/admin/web-batchimport-options.png" width="10cm" align="center" />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <section>
                <title>Structured import</title>
                <para>An hidden feature of the batch import is the possibility to specify some
                    import parameters in more detail. This feature is triggered when the
                    specified folder contains the import-config.xml file. When this happen, this
                    file is read and the standard import switches to the structured one. </para>
                <para>The import-config.xml file has a config root element with the following
                    children: </para>
                
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>categoryMapping [1] : this element specifies the mapping of
                            directories to categories. </para>
                        
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>mapping [0..n] : This element can appear 0 or more times
                                    and maps one directory name to a category name. It must have
                                    a dir attribute that indicates the directory and a to
                                    attribute that indicates the category name. </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>default [1] : This element specifies a default mapping of
                                    categories for all directories that do not match the other
                                    mapping elements. It must have only the to attribute.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>schemaMapping [1] : this element specifies the mapping of
                            directories to metadata schemas. </para>
                        
                        <orderedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>mapping [0..n] : This element can appear 0 or more times
                                    and maps one directory to the schema name that must be used
                                    when importing. The provided schema must match the one used
                                    by the metadata contained into the specified directory,
                                    which must all have the same schema. It must have a dir
                                    attribute that indicates the directory and a to attribute
                                    that indicates the schema name. </para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>default [1] : default behaviour to use when all other
                                    mapping elements do not match. It must have only the to
                                    attribute.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </orderedlist>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>Here is an example of the <literal>import-config.xml</literal> file: </para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[<config>
    <categoryMapping>
        <mapping dir="1" to="maps" />
        <mapping dir="3" to="datasets" />
        <mapping dir="6" to="interactiveResources" />
        <mapping dir="30" to="photo" />
        <default to="maps" />
    </categoryMapping>
    <schemaMapping>
        <mapping dir="3" to="fgdc-std" />
        <default to="dublin-core" />
    </schemaMapping>
</config>]]></programlisting>
                <para>The import procedure starts by scanning the provided directory. This can
                    contain, beside the import-config.xml file, only subdirectories which name
                    will be ignored but used only as a container. Inside each directory, there
                    is another level made only by directories that represent a metadata grouping
                    for categories. Each directory name will be used as the dir attribute in the
                    mapping scheme previously described. </para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>