<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
    <chapter id="basic_configuration">
        <title>Basic configuration</title>
        <section>
            <title>System configuration</title>
            <para>Most of the GeoNetwork’s configuration parameters can be changed using the web
                interface. Those parameters that cannot be changed through the web interface can
                be usually changed using the GAST application. To reach this web interface, you
                must be logged in as an Administrator. The page’s link is located into the
                administration page (<xref linkend="admin_config_where"/>. The link is surrounded with a red
                rectangle). </para>

            <figure id="admin_config_where">
                <title>How to reach the configuration page</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/admin/web-config-where.png" width="12cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>Clicking the page’s link you will get the set of parameters that you can
                change (<xref linkend="admin_config_options"/>). Here follows a detailed description of them: </para>
            <para>Site General site parameters. </para>
            <para>name The name of the GeoNetwork’s installation. This name will be used to
                identify the node in operations like the harvesting. organization The
                organization the node belongs to. Just for informative reasons. Server Here you
                have to enter the address of your GeoNetwork’s node. This address is important
                because it will be used to access the node. </para>
            <para>host The node’s address or IP number. If your node is publicly accessible from
                the Internet, you have to use the machine’s domain/address. If your node is
                hidden into your private network and you have a firewall or web server that
                redirects incoming calls to the node, you have to enter the public address of
                the firewall or web server. A typical configuration is to have an Apache web
                server on address A that is publicly accessible and redirects the requests to a
                Tomcat server on a private address B. In this case you have to enter A in the
                host parameter. port The node’s port (usually 80 or 8080). If the node is
                hidden, you have to enter the port on the public firewall or web server.
                Intranet A common need for an organization is to discriminate between internal
                anonymous users (users that access the node from within the organization) and
                external ones (users from the Internet). Node’s administrators can specify
                different privileges for internal and external anonymous users and, in order to
                do so, they have to specify the parameters of the internal network. </para>
            <para>network The internal network’s address in IP form. netmask The network’s mask.
                Z39.50 GeoNetwork can act as a Z39.50 server, which is an OGC communication
                protocol to query and retrieve metadata. </para>
            <para>enable check this option to start the Z39.50 submodule. Please, notice that
                GeoNetwork must be restarted in order to make this change active. port This is
                the port on which GeoNetwork will be listening for incoming Z39.50 requests.
                Usually, the value of 2100 is a standard one, but to have multiple GeoNetwork
                nodes on the same machine you have to change this value in order to avoid port
                conflicts between the different nodes. Proxy In some occasions (like harvesting)
                GeoNetwork must be able to connect to remote sites and this may be denied if an
                organization uses proxy servers. In this cases, GeoNetwork must be configured to
                use the proxy server in order to route outgoing requests. </para>
            <para>host The proxy’s name or address to use (usually an IP address). port The
                proxy’s port to use. Feedback GeoNetwork can provide some feedback to the
                administrator if some events happen, for example a metadata is downloaded or
                some feedback is provided using the online form. You have to configure
                GeoNetwork with proper parameters to send an email. </para>
            <para>email This is the email address that will be used to send feedback to the
                administrator. SMTP host Organization’s mail server to use when sending emails
                SMTP port Mail server’s SMTP port (usually 25). </para>
                
			 <figure id="admin_config_options">
                <title>The configuration options</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/admin/web-config-options.png" width="11cm" align="center" />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>At the bottom of the page there are some buttons with the following purpose: </para>
            <para>Back Simply returns to the main administration page. Save Saves the current
                options. If some options are invalid, the system will show a dialog with the
                wrong parameter and will focus its textfield on the page. Once the configuration
                is saved a success dialog will be shown. Refresh This button simply refreshes
                the displayed options taking the new values from the server. This can be usefull
                if some options get changed dynamically (for example by another user). </para>
            
            <para>Public host and port usage </para>
            <para>Up to now, the server’s host and port are used in these cases: </para>
            
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>During an editing session, when adding data links to a metadata. The
                        host and port will be used to build download links to store inside the
                        metadata. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>During CSW requests. The GetCapabilities operation returns an XML
                        document with HTTP links to the CSW services. These links are
                        dynamically built using the host and port values.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Localization of dynamic user interface elements</title>
            <para>The user interface of GeoNetwork can be localized into several languages
                through XML language files. But beside static text, there
                is also more dynamic text that can be added and changed interactively.
                This text is stored in the database and is translated 
                using the localization form that is part of the administrative functions
                (<xref linkend="admin_localization_where"/>). </para>
                
			 <figure id="admin_localization_where">
                <title>How to open the localization form</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/admin/web-localization-where.png" width="11cm" align="center" />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>The form allows you to localize the following entities:
                <emphasis>Groups</emphasis>, <emphasis>Categories</emphasis>,
                <emphasis>Operations</emphasis> and <emphasis>Regions</emphasis>. The form
                (<xref linkend="admin_localization_form"/>) subdivided in a left and a right panel. </para>
            <para>The left panel allows you to choose which elements you want to edit. On the top,
                a dropdown let you choose which entity to edit. All elements of the selected
                type are shown in a list. </para>
            <para>When you select an element from the list, the right panel will show the text as 
                it will be displayed in the user interface. The text in the source
                language is read only while you can update the text in the target language field.
                </para>
            <note><para>You can change the source and target languages to best suit your needs. 
                Some users may for instance prefer to translate from French to Spanish, 
                others prefer to work with English as the source language.</para></note>
            <para>Use the Save button to store the updated
                label and move to the next element.</para>
            <important><para>If the user
                changes a label and chooses another target language without saving,
                the label change is lost.</para></important>
			 <figure id="admin_localization_form">
                <title>The localization form</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/admin/web-localization.png" width="11cm" align="center" />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
                
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>