<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
    <chapter id="import_export_tools">
        <title>Import / export tools</title>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <para>Using GAST, you can import and export metadata at will. It allows you to:</para>
            
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Create a <emphasis role="bold">backup</emphasis> of the entire metadata set. 
                        Each metadata has its own file, including maps and other data files. 
                        Once you have the backup, you can decide to import all or only some of them.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Move your metadata</emphasis> from one GeoNetwork catalog to another. This
                        can be done to mirror your metadata or to upgrade an old installation.
                        In the last case, you export your metadata from your old installation
                        and then reimport them into the new one.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Fill the system with <emphasis role="bold">test data</emphasis>. Using the ’skip uuid’ option, you can
                        reimport the same metadata over and over again. This is usefull, for
                        example, if you want to perform stress tests.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>Metadata are exported using the MEF format.</para>
            <important>
                <title>Ownership</title>
                <para>Please, consider that the MEF format version 1.0 does not take into account
                    user and group ownership. When exporting metadata, you loose this information.
                    When importing metadata, the new owner becomes the user that is performing the
                    import while the group ownership is set to null.</para>
            </important>
        </section>
        <section id="mef_import">
            <title>Import</title>
            <para>This tool is located under Management tools on the left panel and
                allows you to import a set of metadata that have been previously exported using
                the export facility (see <xref linkend="mef_export"/>). Selecting the Import tool opens the option
                panel on the right (<xref linkend="admin_import_panel"/>).</para>
            
            <figure id="admin_import_panel">
                <title>The metadata import panel</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/admin/gast-mef-import.png" width="14cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Input folder</title>
                        <para>the source folder in your system that GAST will scan to
                            collect metadata to import. GAST will try to import all files with the mef
                            extension.<note><para>Subfolders are not scanned.</para></note></para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Browse button</title>
                        <para>Navigate through your file system to choose an output
                            location or enter it manually into the textfield.</para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Import</title>
                        <para>This will start the process. A progress dialog will be
                            opened to show the import status.</para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            
        </section>
        <section id="mef_export">
            <title>Export</title>
            <para>This tool is located under the Management tool on the left panel and
                allows you to export a set of metadata using the MEF format. Selecting the Export
                tool opens the option panel on the right (<xref linkend="admin_export_panel"/>).</para>
            
            <figure id="admin_export_panel">
                <title>The metadata export panel</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/admin/gast-mef-export.png" width="14cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Output folder</title>
                        <para>The target folder in your file system where GAST will put the
                            exported metadata. You can either select the Browse button to navigate through
                            your file system to choose a better location or enter it manually in the
                            text field.</para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Format</title>
                        <para>Here you can specify the metadata’s output format. See the MEF
                            specification for more information.</para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Skip UUID</title>
                        <para>Normally this option is not required (see <xref linkend="warn_skipuuid"/>). If you
                            select it, you will loose the metadata’s unique identifier (uuid) but you will
                            be able to reimport that metadata over and over again. This is usefull to fill
                            the system with test data.</para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Search</title>
                        <para>Allows to specify free text search criteria to limit the set of exported records.
                            <note><para>the export result will depend on the metadata visible to
                            the searching user. If you do not authenticate, you will get only public
                            metadata.</para></note></para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <formalpara>
                        <title>Export</title>
                        <para>This will start the export process. A progress dialog will be
                            opened to show the export status.</para>
                    </formalpara>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <warning id="warn_skipuuid"><para>Skipping the UUID on import or export can cause metadata to be duplicated. 
                This should normally always be avoided</para></warning>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>