<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
    <appendix id="faq">
        <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
        <qandaset>
            <qandadiv>
                <title>Users FAQ</title>
                <qandaentry>
                    <question>
                        <para>Where do I learn more about the use and functionality of the
                            GeoNetwork opensource catalog?</para>
                    </question>
                    <answer>
                        <para>The Quick Start Guide will provide you with an excellent first
                            introduction. The Guide can be downloaded from the <ulink
                                url="http://geonetwork-opensource.org">GeoNetwork Community
                            website</ulink>
                       </para>
                    </answer>
                </qandaentry>
            </qandadiv>
            <qandadiv>
                <title>Administrators FAQ</title>
                <qandaentry>
                    <question>
                        <para>I am having difficulty installing multiple instances of GeoNetwork on
                            the same server</para>
                    </question>
                    <answer>
                        <para>To run multiple installation you have to change the ports that
                            GeoNetwork uses in order to avoid conflicts. The port are:</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <formalpara>
                                    <title>Z39.50 listening port</title>
                                    <para>This is the most probable source of conflicts. You have to
                                        entedit the <literal>web/WEB-INF/config.xml</literal> file of the second
                                        installation and choose a value other than the default one,
                                        which is 2100. Use for example 2101 but keep in mind that
                                        remote nodes usually use 2100 so your second node will not
                                        be reachable. You cannot use the system configuration web
                                        form the first time because if the port conflicts, the
                                        server won't start.</para>
                                </formalpara>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <formalpara>
                                    <title>If you are using Jetty</title>
                                    <para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <formalpara>
                                                  <title>Jetty's listening port</title>
                                                  <para>This can be modified using GAST and its
                                                  default value is usually 8080. To run a
                                                  second installation use a different value,
                                                  like 8081. The affected file is
                                                  bin/jetty.xml.</para>
                                                </formalpara>
                                            </listitem>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <formalpara>
                                                  <title>Jetty's stop port</title>
                                                  <para>This is defined into the scripts
                                                  <literal>bin/start-geonetwork.*</literal> and
                                                  <literal>bin/stop-geonetwork.*</literal> (for both Windows and
                                                  Linux). The provided value is 8079 as the
                                                  value of the STOP.PORT parameter. Use
                                                  another value for the second installation,
                                                  like 8078. If you don't change this value,
                                                  the stop script will stop all
                                                  instances.</para>
                                                </formalpara>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                   </para>
                                </formalpara>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <formalpara>
                                    <title>If you are using the embedded McKoi DBMS</title>
                                    <para>
                                        <itemizedlist>
                                            <listitem>
                                                <formalpara>
                                                  <title>McKoi listening port</title>
                                                  <para>This can be easily modified using GAST.
                                                  The default value is 9157. For other
                                                  installations you can use 9158, 9159 and so
                                                  on. The affected files are
                                                  <literal>web/WEB-INF/config.xml</literal> and
                                                  <literal>web/WEB-INF/db/db.conf</literal>.</para>
                                                </formalpara>
                                            </listitem>
                                        </itemizedlist>
                                   </para>
                                </formalpara>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </answer>
                </qandaentry>
                <qandaentry>
                    <question>
                        <para>What is normally logged when running GeoNetwork opensource?</para>
                    </question>
                    <answer>
                        <para>GeoNetwork has its own internal logging based on
                            <ulink url="http://logging.apache.org/log4j">log4j Logging services</ulink> (written to the
                            file jeeves.log). Additionaly there are log files generated by the web
                            server (<ulink url="http://jetty.mortbay.org/jetty">Jetty</ulink> ,
                            <ulink url="http://tomcat.apache.org/">Apache Tomcat</ulink> etc..) and by the DBMS used
                            (for example by the internal <ulink url="http://www.mckoi.com/database/">McKoi SQL</ulink>
                            ).</para>
                    </answer>
                </qandaentry>
                <qandaentry>
                    <question>
                        <para>How do I control what is written to the GeoNetwork internal log file?
                       </para>
                    </question>
                    <answer>
                        <para>The logging is configured in the file <literal>../web/WEB-INF/log4j.cfg</literal> . You
                            can change the settings by editing the file in a text editor. For
                            operational systems it is suggested to put all log options to OFF or
                            FATAL. The log options are, with increasing log intensity:</para>
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>OFF - The OFF Level has the highest possible rank and is
                                    intended to turn off logging.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>FATAL - The FATAL level designates very severe error events
                                    that will presumably lead the application to abort.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>ERROR - The ERROR level designates error events that might
                                    still allow the application to continue running.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>WARN - The WARN level designates potentially harmful
                                    situations.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>INFO - The INFO level designates informational messages that
                                    highlight the progress of the application at coarse-grained
                                    level.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>DEBUG - The DEBUG Level designates fine-grained informational
                                    events that are most useful to debug an application.</para>
                            </listitem>
                            <listitem>
                                <para>ALL - The ALL Level has the lowest possible rank and is
                                    intended to turn on all logging.</para>
                            </listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </answer>
                </qandaentry>

            </qandadiv>
            <qandadiv>
                <title>Developers FAQ</title>
                <qandaentry>
                    <question>
                        <para>What is Free and Open Source Software (FOSS) and how can I use,
                            participate and contribute to the GeoNetwork opensource project?</para>
                    </question>
                    <answer>
                        <para>The book "Producing Open Source Software" (shown in <xref
                                linkend="producingoss"/>) is a highly recommended book for anyone
                            working on open source software projects. It provides insight in all
                            aspects of FOSS development and on how to make a project succesful. If
                            you are interested in participating in the GeoNetwork opensource
                            project, please spend some time reading through this book. It's
                            definitely worth the time and money (so buy the hardcopy if you can
                            afford it!).</para>

                        <para>Producing Open Source Software is a book about the human side of open
                            source development. It describes how successful projects operate, the
                            expectations of users and developers, and the culture of free software.</para>

                        <para>The book is available in bookstores and from the publisher (<ulink
                                url="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/producingoss/">O'Reilly
                            Media</ulink>), or you can browse or download it from
                            <ulink url="http://producingoss.com/"/>. Producing Open Source Software is released
                            under an open copyright that allows everyone to share and modify the
                            book freely. The latest version is always available on the website. The
                            online version is the same as the commercially available print version ?
                            in other words, you can buy a printed copy and know that it's
                            up-to-date.</para>
                        <figure id="producingoss">
                            <title>Producing Open Source Software</title>
                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata fileref="images/producingoss-cover-small.png" align="center"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </answer>
                </qandaentry>
            </qandadiv>
        </qandaset>
     </appendix>

    <!-- 
        Introduction
        
        This document collects most of the FAQs about GeoNetwork 
        opensource, both from a user, an administrator and a developer's 
        point of view.
        -->
</book>
