<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
    <preface id="preface">
        <title>Preface</title>
        <formalpara>
            <title>About this Project</title>
            <para>This document provides guidelines to use and customize the GeoNetwork opensource software. 
                This project started out as a Spatial Data Catalog System for the 
                <ulink url="http://www.fao.org">Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations 
                (FAO)</ulink>, the 
                <ulink url="http://vam.wfp.org">United Nations World Food Programme (WFP)</ulink> 
                and the <ulink url="http://www.unep.org">United Nations Environmental Programme (UNEP)</ulink>.
                At present the project is widely used as the basis of Spatial
                Data Infrastructures all around the world. The project is part of the 
                Open Source Geospatial Foundation (OSGeo) and can be found at 
                <ulink url="http://geonetwork-opensource.org"/>.
            </para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
            <title>License Information</title>
            <para>
                Copyright (c) 2007-2008 Open Source Geospatial Foundation (<ulink url="http://www.osgeo.org">OSGeo</ulink>).  
            </para>
        </formalpara>
        <para>You are free to Share — to copy, distribute and transmit the work. 
            Under the following conditions:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>Attribution. You must attribute the work in the manner specified 
                    by the author or licensor (but not in any way that suggests that they 
                    endorse you or your use of the work).</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>No Derivative Works. You may not alter, transform, or 
                    build upon this work.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>For any reuse or distribution, you must make clear to others 
                    the license terms of this work. The best way to do this is with a link to 
                    this web page.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Any of the above conditions can be waived if you get permission
                    from the copyright holder.</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>Nothing in this license impairs or restricts the author's moral
                    rights.</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>You may obtain a copy of the License at
            <ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/3.0/">Creative Commons</ulink></para>
        <para>The document is written in DocBook format for consistency and portability.</para>
        <formalpara>
            <title>Author Information</title>
            <para>This framework and documentation was written by the GeoNetwork opensource
                Developers. If you have questions, found a bug or have
                enhancements, please contact us through the GeoNetwork opensource Development
                Mailing list at <email>geonetwork-devel@lists.sourceforge.net</email></para>
        </formalpara>
        <para/>
        <para><inlinemediaobject id="gn_logo"><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/GeoNetwork_opensource_logo.jpg" width="4cm" contentwidth="4cm"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject></para>
        <para/>
        <para><inlinemediaobject id="osgeo_logo"><imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/OSGeo_logo.jpg" width="4cm" contentwidth="4cm"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject></para>
        
    </preface>
</book>
