<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
    <chapter id="getting_started">
        <title>Getting Started</title>
        <indexterm><primary>login</primary></indexterm>
        
        <para>Please make sure you have opened the homepage of the GeoNetwork based 
            catalog.<footnote><para>If you installed the software on your local machine
            and started it, the default URL is <ulink url="http://localhost:8080/geonetwork"/></para></footnote></para>
    
        <para>There are many different ways to search the catalogue for maps and other geographic
            data. This guide will introduce you to the most popular search methods: default,
            advanced and by category. Whichever search you choose, remember that you will see
            results based on your privileges and assigned work group (<xref linkend="privileges"/>).</para>
        
        <para>Note that the term <emphasis role="bold">data</emphasis> in this application refers to
            datasets, maps, tables, documents, etc. that are linked to the metadata of a specific
            record.</para>

        <section>
            <title>Default Search</title>

            <para>The default search allows you to search text within the entire record, such as
                keywords of the metadata and/or geographic location.</para>

            <formalpara>            
                <title>Free text search</title>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>Type</emphasis> a search term in the 
                    <emphasis>What?</emphasis> field. You can type anything here 
                    (free text). You can use quotes around text to find exact combinations of words.
                </para>
            </formalpara>
            <para>Text and operators (and, or, not) are not case
                sensitive. (See <xref linkend="simple_free_text"/>).</para>

            <figure id="simple_free_text">
                <title>The free text field</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/what.png" width="5cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <formalpara>
                <title>Geographic search</title>
                    <para>For the geographic search, two options are available for selecting a particular
                    region to limit the search:</para>
            </formalpara>
    
            <para>You can select a <emphasis role="bold">region</emphasis> 
                from a predefined list (<xref linkend="simple_region_field"/>);</para>
    
            <figure id="simple_region_field">
                <title>The region field</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/where1.png" width="5cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>You can select your own <emphasis>area of interest</emphasis>
                in a more interactive way. A small global map is shown on the screen from which you can
                drag and drop the frame of your location area. Just click on the
                button on the upper right of the map screen (<xref linkend="aoi_map"/>);</para>

            <figure id="aoi_map">
                <title>Interactive Area Of Interest map</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/where2.png" width="5cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            
            
            <formalpara>
                <title>Perform search</title>
                <para>Both types of search, free text search and geographic search can be combined to
                restrict the query further.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <para>Click the <literal>Search</literal> button to proceed and show the results.
                (<xref linkend="search_button"/>).</para>

            <figure id="search_button">
                <title>The Search button</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/search_button.png" width="3cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Searching by Categories</title>

            <para>An additional way to search data within the GeoNetwork database, from the home
                page, is searching by <emphasis role="bold">Category</emphasis>. A list of
                categories is provided to the user to identify data at a more generic level:
                    <emphasis role="bold">Applications</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold"
                >Audio/Video</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Case study and best
                practices</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Conference proceedings</emphasis>,
                    <emphasis role="bold">Datasets</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold"
                >Directories</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Interactive resources</emphasis>,
                    <emphasis role="bold">Maps and graphics</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Other
                    information resources</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Photo</emphasis>.</para>

            <para>To search only for maps, click on <emphasis role="bold">Maps and
                Graphics</emphasis> (<xref linkend="categories"/>). A list of maps will be displayed from which you
                may view details of every single map; just clicking on the <emphasis role="bold"
                    >Metadata</emphasis> button of the map you wish to review.</para>

            <figure id="categories">
                <title>Search by Category</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/Categories.png" width="6cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Advanced Search</title>

            <para>The advanced search option (<xref linkend="advanced_search"/>) works similarly to the default search.
                However, you can be more specific in your search criteria as it offers different
                elements to look for data, each of them focussing one of the following aspects: <emphasis role="bold">What?, Where?, When?</emphasis>
            </para>

            <figure id="advanced_search">
                <title>Advanced search options</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/advanced_search1.png" width="14cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>To perform an <emphasis role="bold">
                    <emphasis>advanced search</emphasis>
                </emphasis>, from the home page <emphasis role="bold">click</emphasis>
                <emphasis role="bold">Advanced </emphasis>just below the search bottom (see <xref linkend="advanced_search_button"/>).</para>

            <figure id="advanced_search_button">
                <title>Show advanced search options</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/advanced_search_button.png" width="3cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>In the <emphasis role="bold">WHAT?</emphasis> section the elements are all related
                to the data content. Through them, in addition to searching only free keywords in
                the entire metadata content, you can also search directly in the title or abstract
                fields and add more keywords to customize your search further. You can also specify
                the level of accuracy you wish to reach in performing your search (<xref linkend="adv_what_options"/>).</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>To search by <emphasis role="bold">Title</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold"
                            >Abstract</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Free Text</emphasis>, or
                            <emphasis role="bold">Keyword</emphasis>(s) type any text into the
                        respective field. You can enter information in one or multiple field(s). If
                        you do not want to search by a given field, simply leave it blank;</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>You can choose the <emphasis role="bold">accuracy of your
                        search</emphasis>, in terms of spelling words, from <emphasis role="bold"
                            >Precise</emphasis> = 1 to <emphasis role="bold">Imprecise</emphasis> =
                        0.2, through 3 more consecutive steps which are equal to 0.8, 0.6,
                    0.4.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <figure id="adv_what_options">
                <title>"What" section in the Advanced search</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/advanced_search_what.png" width="5cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">WHERE?</emphasis> parameters, which are related to the
                spatial extent, allow you, as in the default search, either to select your own area
                of interest or to select a predefined region from the drop-down list. In this
                section you can also type the geographic coordinates of a specific location that is
                not available from the above list. (<xref linkend="adv_where_options"/>)</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>To select <emphasis role="bold">your own area of interest</emphasis>, drag
                        and drop the frame of your area on the global map using the appropriate tool
                        on the bottom left of the map screen;</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>To use <emphasis role="bold">free coordinates</emphasis>, type the
                        lat-long geographic references in the appropriate fields around the map
                        screen, without any limitation of decimal figures;</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>To use the coordinates of a <emphasis role="bold">predefined
                        region</emphasis>, select the region from the drop-down list.</para>

                    <para/>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <figure id="adv_where_options">
                <title>"Where" section in the Advanced search</title>
                
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/advanced_search_where.png" width="8cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>Whatever type of geographic search you decide to perform, in the <emphasis
                    role="bold">Spatial search type</emphasis> field, you can choose from different
                options: <emphasis role="bold">is</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold"
                >overlaps</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">encloses</emphasis>, <emphasis
                    role="bold">is fully outside of</emphasis> (<xref linkend="adv_where_options"/>). If you use this
                field, be cautious as this limits your output data as follows:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If you choose <emphasis role="bold">Spatial search type</emphasis>
                        <citetitle>is</citetitle> “Country”, only maps for the selected country will
                        be displayed. In other words, a city map within that country will not show
                        in the output results.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>If you choose <emphasis role="bold">Spatial search type</emphasis>
                        <citetitle>overlaps</citetitle> “Country”, all maps with the bounding box
                        overlapping that country will be displayed in the results, i.e. the
                        neighbouring countries, the continent of which that country is part of and
                        the global maps.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>If you choose <emphasis role="bold">Spatial search type</emphasis>
                        <citetitle>encloses</citetitle> “Country” you will get, in the output
                        results, maps of that country first and then all maps within its bounding
                        box.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Similarly, if you choose <emphasis role="bold">Spatial search type</emphasis>
                        <citetitle>is fully outside of</citetitle> a selected region, only maps that
                        follow that exact criteria will show in the output results.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>The <emphasis role="bold">WHEN?</emphasis> section gives you the possibility to
                restrict your search in terms of temporal extent, indicating a specific range of
                time referred to the data creation or publication date (<xref linkend="adv_when_options"/>).</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>To specify a range of time, click on the date selector button next to
                            <emphasis role="bold">From – To</emphasis> fields. Make use of the
                            symbols<emphasis role="bold"> &gt;</emphasis> and <emphasis
                            role="bold">&gt;&gt;</emphasis> on top of the calendar to select
                        the month and the year first and then click on the exact day; a complete
                        date will be filled in using the following standard order: YY-MM-DD.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>To clean the time fields, simply click on the white cross on their right;
                        the box <emphasis role="bold">Any</emphasis> will be automatically selected
                        and the search will be performed without any restriction on the time
                    period.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <figure id="adv_when_options">
                <title>"When" section in the Advanced search</title>
                
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/advanced_search_when.png" width="8cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>Finally, the advanced search allows you to apply further restrictions on the basis
                of additional parameters as data source, data categories and data format (<xref linkend="adv_more_options"/>).</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>To limit your queries to only one <emphasis role="bold">Catalog</emphasis>
                        out of those made available by the installation through the harvesting
                        process, highlight the catalog of preference or just keep <emphasis
                            role="bold">Any</emphasis> selected to search all sites. (See more info
                        about <emphasis role="bold">data harvesting</emphasis> in Section 4 Chapter
                        1 of these guidelines).</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>To search for data organized by <emphasis role="bold">Category</emphasis>,
                        such as Applications, Datasets, etc., simply highlight the category you wish
                        to search in from the related drop-down list, otherwise we suggest to leave
                        this field in <emphasis role="bold">Any</emphasis> Category.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>You can search for <emphasis role="bold">Digital</emphasis> or <emphasis
                            role="bold">Hard Copy</emphasis> maps. To search in one or the other,
                        simply check the box next to the one you wish to search. If no box is
                        checked, all content will be searched.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>At last, you can customize the number of output results per page in the <emphasis
                    role="bold">Hits Per Page</emphasis> field. Simply highlight the number of
                records to be displayed or leave the field set on the default number (10).</para>

            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Click the <emphasis role="bold">Search</emphasis> button.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <figure id="adv_more_options">
                <title>Other options in the Advanced search</title>
                
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/advanced_search_morerest.png" width="8cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Analyzing Search Results</title>

            <para>The output of a search provides you a list of the metadata records that should fit
                your request. For each record, the result page shows the title, an abstract and the
                keywords. According to the privileges that have been set for each metadata, a
                maximum of four sections can be consulted, as shown below. (<xref linkend="search_output"/>)</para>

            <para>
                <figure id="search_output">
                    <title>Search results</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/search_output2.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Metadata</emphasis>: The metadata section describes
                        the dataset (e.g.: citation, data owner, temporal/spatial/methodological
                        information) and could contain links to other web sites that could provide
                        further information about the dataset.</para>

                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Download</emphasis>: Depending on the privileges
                        that have been set for each record, when this button is present, the dataset
                        is available and downloadable. The process for retrieving data is simple and quick by
                        just clicking the download button (<xref linkend="search_result_resource"/>) or by using the proper link
                        in the specific metadata section for distribution info in the full metadata view (<xref linkend="online_resources"/>).</para>

                    <para>
                        <figure id="search_result_resource">
                            <title>A single search result</title>

                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata fileref="images/search_output1.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </para>

                    <para>
                        <figure id="online_resources">
                            <title>Available services related to the resource</title>

                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata fileref="images/download.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Interactive Map</emphasis>: The map service is also
                        optional. When this button is shown, an interactive map for this layer is
                        available and, by default, it will be displayed on the map screen of the
                        simple search. To better visualize the map through the map viewer, <emphasis
                            role="bold">click</emphasis> on <emphasis role="bold">Open Map
                        Viewer</emphasis> on the bottom left of the map screen (<xref linkend="interactive_map"/>).</para>

                    <para>
                        <figure id="interactive_map">
                            <title>The interactive map viewer</title>

                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata fileref="images/interactive_map.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Graphic Overviews</emphasis>: There are small and
                        large overviews of the map used to properly evaluate usefulness of the data,
                        especially if the interactive map is not available. Simply click on the
                        small image to enlarge it. (<xref linkend="large_thumbnail"/>)</para>

                    <para>
                        <figure id="large_thumbnail">
                            <title>Large preview image</title>

                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata fileref="images/thumbnail.png" width="10cm" align="center"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>

        </section>
        <section id="privileges">
            <title>Privileges, roles and user groups</title>
            <indexterm><primary>security</primary><secondary>privileges</secondary></indexterm>
            <indexterm><primary>security</primary><secondary>roles</secondary></indexterm>
            <indexterm><primary>security</primary><secondary>user groups</secondary></indexterm>
            <indexterm><primary>security</primary><secondary>access restrictions</secondary></indexterm>
            
            <para>GeoNetwork uses a system of <emphasis>Privileges</emphasis> 
                ,<emphasis>Roles</emphasis> and <emphasis>User groups</emphasis>.</para>
            <para>There are no restrictions for users to search and access
                <emphasis role="bold">public information</emphasis> in a GeoNetwork opensource based catalog. To get access to
                <emphasis role="bold">restricted information</emphasis> or advanced functionality, an account to log
                in is required. This should be provided by the GNos
                administrator.</para>
            <para>To log in, simply go to the homepage and enter your username and password in the
                dedicated fields on the top right corner, then click the login button.
                (See <xref linkend="login"/>)</para>
            
            <figure id="login">
                <title>Login</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/login.png" width="7cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Privileges</title>
                <para>Depending on the privileges set on a metadata record and on your role
                    as an authenticated user, you will be able to read about a resource and
                    download or interactively browse data related to that resource.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Roles</title>
                <para>Users with an <emphasis>Editor</emphasis> role can create, import and edit 
                    metadata records. They can also upload data and configure links to interactive 
                    map services.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>User groups</title>
                <para>Every authenticated user is assigned to a particular
                    work group and is able to view data within that work group.</para>
            </formalpara>
        </section>
        
    </chapter>

</book>
