<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
    <chapter id="metadata">
        <title>Metadata in Spatial Data Management</title><indexterm><primary>metadata</primary></indexterm>
        <section>
            <title>What is Metadata?</title>

            <para>Metadata, commonly defined as “data about data” or "information about data", is a structured set of
                information which describes data (including both digital and non-digital datasets)
                stored in administrative systems. Metadata may provide a short summary about the
                content, purpose, quality, location of the data as well as information related to
                its creation.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>What are Metadata Standards?</title><indexterm><primary>Metadata</primary><secondary>standards</secondary></indexterm>
            <para>Metadata standards provide data producers with the format and content for properly
                describing their data, allowing users to evaluate the usefulness of the data in
                addressing their specific needs.</para>
            
            <para>The standards provide a documented, common set of terms and definitions
                that are presented in a structured format.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Why do we need Standardized Metadata?</title>

            <para>Standardized metadata support users in effectively and efficiently accessing data
                by using a common set of terminology and metadata elements that allow for a quick
                means of data discovery and retrieval from metadata clearinghouses. The metadata
                based on standards ensure information consistency and quality and avoid that
                important parts of data knowledge are lost.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Geographic Information Metadata Standard</title><indexterm><primary>Metadata</primary><secondary>ISO19115</secondary></indexterm>
            <indexterm><primary>Metadata</primary><secondary>ISO19139</secondary></indexterm>
            <indexterm><primary>Metadata</primary><secondary>FGDC</secondary></indexterm>
            <indexterm><primary>Metadata</primary><secondary>Dublin Core</secondary></indexterm>
            <para>Geographic data, which can be defined as any data with a geographic component, is
                often produced by one individual or organization, and may address the needs of
                various users, including information system analysts, programme planners, developers
                of geographic information or policy makers. Proper standard documentation on
                geographic data enable different users to better evaluate the appropriateness of
                data to be used for data production, storage, update.</para>

            <para>The metadata standards supported by GeoNetwork opensource are the <emphasis
                    role="bold"><emphasis role="bold">ISO 19115</emphasis>:2003</emphasis> -
                approved by the international community in April 2003 as a tool to define metadata
                in the field of geographic information - and the <emphasis role="bold"
                >FGDC</emphasis> - the metadata standard adopted in the United States by the Federal
                Geographic Data Committee. In addition, GNos supports also the international
                standard <emphasis role="bold">Dublin Core</emphasis> for the description of general
                documents.</para>

            <para>This ISO Standard precisely defines how geographic information and related
                services should be described, providing mandatory and conditional metadata sections,
                metadata entities and metadata elements. This standard applies to data series,
                independent datasets, individual geographic features and feature properties. Despite
                ISO 19115:2003 was designed for digital data, its principles can be extended to many
                other forms of geographic data such as maps, charts, and textual documents as well
                as non-geographic data.</para>
            
            <para>The underlying format of an ISO19115:2003 compliant metadata is XML. GeoNetwork 
                uses the <literal>ISO Technical Specification 19139 Geographic information - Metadata - 
                XML schema implementation</literal> for the encoding of this XML.</para>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Metadata profiles</title><indexterm><primary>Metadata</primary><secondary>profiles</secondary></indexterm>
            <para>GeoNetwork supports multiple metadata profiles. Profiles can take the form of 
                <literal>Templates</literal> that you can create using the metadata editor. 
                Using the Advanced view of the editor, virtually all of the metadata elements
                are accessible to the user.</para>
            
            <para>Support for extensions to a metadata standard can also be achieved relatively
                quick by an experienced XML/XSL software engineer.</para>
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Transition between metadata standards</title><indexterm><primary>Metadata</primary><secondary>transforming</secondary></indexterm>
            <indexterm><primary>Metadata</primary><secondary>migrating</secondary></indexterm>
            <para>With the ISO19115:2003 Metadata standard for Geographic Information now
                being the preferred common standard, many have a need to migrate legacy metadata
                into the new standard.</para>
            <para>GeoNetwork provides import (and export) functionality and has a number of 
                transformers in place. It is an easy process for a system administrator to 
                install custom transformers based on XSLT.</para>
        </section>
        
    </chapter>
</book>
