<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
    <chapter id="installing">
        <title>Installing the software</title>

        <section>
            <title>New version - New funtionalities</title>

            <para>The new GeoNetwork opensource comes with substantial upgrades of different
                components for a more intuitive and responsive user-system interaction. Web2
                technologies have been adopted, in particular AJAX techniques, to allow for more
                interactive and faster services in the web interface and for the integration of the
                existing web map viewer in the home page. Similar functionalities have been
                implemented in the administrative part of the system, to provide an easier access to
                the configuration pages related to site settings, catalogue harvesting, scheduling
                and maintenance.</para>

            <para>The search interface has been completely overhauled to provide highly interactive
                searching capabilities. Furthermore, the new version of GNos embeds GeoServer as map
                server. Users can now not only overlay OGC web map services available on the web,
                but also create their own map services for other users to browse without having to
                download additional plugins. Maps created with web map services can be now saved as
                PDF and sent to others.</para>

            <para>The metadata catalogue handles the latest ISO19115:2003 geographic metadata format
                based on the ISO19139:2007 schemas, as well as the older ISO19115 final draft format,
                FGDC and Dublin Core. The metadata editor is able to handle the majority of these
                complex standards, providing default, advanced and XML editing online tools.</para>

            <para>The new version has a number of different harvesting interfaces allowing users to
                connect their own server to many other catalogues around the world. This is the
                result of the implementation of the open source reference for the web catalog
                services according to OGC specifications. Harvesting in the new version is fully
                compatible with GeoNetwork 2.0 and higher nodes.</para>

            <para>We have added avanced online and offline administration funcionalities to
                configure, backup and migrate the application. We have also added a convenient
                import and export format "MEF" or <literal>Metadata Exchange Format</literal>, 
                that allows the users to
                move metadata, previews and even data in a convenient single file. GNos can be
                easily expanded with plugins to export/import metadata to/from other software
                supporting MEF.</para>

            <para/>

            <figure id="home_page_of_gn">
                <title>
                    Standard home page of GeoNetwork opensource
                </title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/Home_page_s.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para/>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Where do I get the installer?</title>

            <para>You can find the software on the Internet at the 
                <ulink url="http://geonetwork-opensource.org">GeoNetwork
                opensource Community website</ulink>. The software is also distributed 
                through the SourceForge.net Website at
                <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/geonetwork"/>.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>System requirements</title>
            <para>GeoNetwork can run either on <emphasis role="bold">MS Windows</emphasis>, <emphasis
                    role="bold">Linux</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">Mac OS X</emphasis>.</para>

            <para>Some general system requirements for the software to run without problems are
                listed below:</para>

            <para><emphasis role="bold">Processor</emphasis>: 1 GHz or higher</para>

            <para><emphasis role="bold">Memory (RAM)</emphasis>: 512 MB or higher</para>

            <para><emphasis role="bold">Disk Space</emphasis>: 30 MB minimum. However, it is
                suggested to have a minimum of 250 MB of free disk space. Additional space is
                required depending on the amount of spatial data that you expect to upload into the
                internal geodatabse.</para>

            <para><emphasis role="bold">Other Software requirements</emphasis>: A Java Runtime
                Environment (JRE 1.5.0). For server installations, Apache Tomcat and a dedicated
                JDBC compliant DBMS (MySQL, Oracle) are also required.<emphasis role="bold"/></para>

            <section>
                <title>Additional Software</title>
                <para>The software listed here is not required to install GeoNetwork, but can be used
                      for custom installations.</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>MySQL DBMS v5.5+ (All)<footnote id="all_os"><para>All = Windows, Linux and Mac OS X</para></footnote></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Apache Tomcat v5.5 (All)<footnoteref linkend="all_os"/></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Apache HTTP v2.0+ (Windows), optional</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Druid v3.8 (All)<footnoteref linkend="all_os"/></para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
             </section>
            
            <section>
                <title>Supported browsers</title>
                <para>GeoNetwork should work normally with the following browsers:</para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Firefox v1.5+ (All)<footnoteref linkend="all_os"/></para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Internet Explorer v6+ (Windows)</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Safari v3+ (Mac OS X Leopard)<footnoteref linkend="all_os"/></para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
        </section>
        
        <?hard-pagebreak?>
        <section>
            <title>How do I install GeoNetwork opensource?</title>

            <para>Before running the GeoNetwork installer, make sure that all system requirements
                are satisfied, and in particular that the Java Runtime Environment version 1.5.0 is
                set up on your machine.</para>

            <para>If you use Windows, the following steps will guide you to complete the
                installation (other FOSS will follow):</para>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Double click on <emphasis role="bold"
                        >geonetwork-install-2.1.0.exe</emphasis> to start the GeoNetwok opensource
                        desktop installer</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Follow the instructions on screen (<xref linkend="installer"/>)</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>After completion of the installation process, a 'GeoNetwork desktop' menu
                        will be added to your Windows Start menu under 'Programs'</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Click Start &gt; Programs &gt; GeoNetwork desktop &gt; Start
                        server to start the Geonetwork opensource Web server. The first time you do
                        this, the system will require about 1 minute to complete startup.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Click Start &gt; Programs &gt; Geonetwork desktop &gt; Open
                        GeoNetwork opensource to start using GeoNetwork opensource, or connect your
                        Web browser to <ulink url="http://localhost8080/geonetwork/"/></para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>

            <para/>

            <figure id="installer">
                <title>Installer</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/installer.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>
                <guilabel/>
            </para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
