<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
    <chapter id="adding_new_data_and_information">
        <title>Adding new Data and Information</title>

        <para>This section guides you through the process of adding new records (new data with
            information) into the GeoNetwork catalogue using either the online metadata editor or
            the advanced metadata insert tool, based on XML documents. In both cases you will use
            the template system, add thumbnails, upload data, link to services and set access
            privileges to the metadata and data.</para>

        <para>To add or edit data and metadata, you must be <emphasis role="bold"
            >registered</emphasis> as an <emphasis role="bold">Editor</emphasis> into the work group
            you want to add records to. Contact your administrator if you are not a registered
            editor for your work group.</para>

        <para>For the metadata creation using the online editor, GNos provides a set of simplified
            metadata templates based on the cited standards: ISO, FGDC and DC. The templates for
            vector and raster based on the ISO 19139 are the preferred ones since they are devised
            in a way that hides the complexity of the ISO19115 standard in the default view. At the
            same time those templates are extensible with new elements to fit specialized needs
            through the advanced view.</para>

        <para>To produce a good metadata record, always try to gather as much details as possible on
            the resource that you want to describe taking into account the metadata elements that
            have been presented in the previous chapter. The next step is to fill out properly the
            fields provided by the metadata templates, while at the same time avoiding duplication
            of information throughout the form.</para>

        <para>The most important fields that may not be waived while compiling a standard based
            metadata record are the following: <emphasis role="bold">Title, Date of Creation o
                Publication, Abstract, Language used for documenting data, Topic Category, Scale,
                Maintenance and Update Frequency, Metadata Author, Language Used for Documenting
                Metadata</emphasis>.</para>

        <para>In addition to the main mandatory fields, we recommend you to fill out these optional
            but critical fields (if information is available): <emphasis role="bold">Purpose -
                Keywords - Presentation Form - Status - Spatial Representation Type - Geographic
                Location - Reference System Info - Temporal Extent - Data Quality Info - Access and
                Use Constraints - Point of Contact - Distribution Info: Online Resources.</emphasis></para>

        <para>
            <emphasis>
                <emphasis>You should also prepare an image of your data that is required to be
                    displayed in search results as thumbnail.</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
        </para>

        <para>
            <emphasis>
                <emphasis>Next section will guide you through the process of metadata creation using
                    the online editor.</emphasis>
            </emphasis>
        </para>

        <section>
            <title>Creating a New Record using the Metadata Editor on line</title>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>In the home page, click on the <emphasis role="bold">Administration
                        Tab</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Select <emphasis role="bold">New Metadata</emphasis> from the List of the
                        admin page.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Select the metadata standard <emphasis role="bold">Template</emphasis>, if
                        possible, using the preferred ones (<xref linkend="metadata_creation"/>).
                        GeoNetwork opensource comes by default with support for three metadata
                        standards, ISO19139, FGDC and Dublin core. For the ISO standard, two
                        templates have been developed; one for vector and one for raster data. Both
                        contain a relevant set of elements to describe the respective types of data.
                        More templates can be developed online.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Select the <emphasis role="bold">Group</emphasis> the metadata will belong
                        to. These are the groups authorized to add metadata to by your
                        administrator.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Click on <emphasis role="bold">Create</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>

            <section>
                <title>The steps in more details</title>

                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Enter your username and password and click on the login button (<xref
                                linkend="login_adding"/>). The system will identify you and assign
                            the correct privileges to work with.</para>

                        <figure id="login_adding">
                            <title>Login</title>

                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata fileref="images/login.png" width="6cm" align="center"/>
                                </imageobject>
                                <textobject>
                                    <phrase>Login</phrase>
                                </textobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Open the Administration page by clicking the Administration button in
                            the banner and then click on the New metadata link (<xref
                                linkend="admin_panel"/>).</para>

                        <figure id="admin_panel">
                            <title>Administration panel</title>

                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata fileref="images/Admin.png" width="12cm" align="center"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>From the metadata creation page, select the metadata standard to use
                            from the dropdown list (<xref linkend="metadata_creation"/>)</para>

                        <para>
                            <figure id="metadata_creation">
                                <title>Template selection</title>

                                <mediaobject>
                                    <imageobject>
                                        <imagedata fileref="images/metadataCreation.png"
                                            width="10cm" align="center"/>
                                    </imageobject>
                                </mediaobject>
                            </figure>
                        </para>

                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>After selecting the correct template, you should identify which group
                            of users the metadata will belong to (<xref linkend="select_group"/>)
                            and finally click on <emphasis role="bold">Create</emphasis>.</para>

                        <figure id="select_group">
                            <title>Group selection</title>

                            <mediaobject>
                                <imageobject>
                                    <imagedata fileref="images/selectGroup.png" width="10cm" align="center"/>
                                </imageobject>
                            </mediaobject>
                        </figure>

                        <para>A new metadata form based on the selected template will be displayed
                            for you to fill out.</para>

                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Switching Editing Views from Default to Advanced to XML View</title>

                <para>Once you create a new record, you can choose between <emphasis role="bold"
                        >Default</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">Advanced</emphasis> or <emphasis
                        role="bold">XML View</emphasis>. To switch view, simply click on the view
                    you want to switch to on the left column of the page. The view in <emphasis
                        role="bold">bold</emphasis> is the view you are currently using (<xref
                        linkend="switch_views"/>).</para>

                <figure id="switch_views">
                    <title>Metadata view options</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/switchViews.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>In the previous chapter you have analyzed the metadata structure as it is
                    presented in the <emphasis role="bold">Default View</emphasis>. A selection of
                    the main fields from different categories of information is shown in one single
                    view. The minimum set of metadata required to serve the full range of metadata
                    applications (data discovery, determination of data fitness for use, data
                    access, data transfer and use of digital data) is defined here, along with
                    optional metadata elements to allow for a more extensive standard description of
                    geographic data, if required. However, if should be there a need to add more
                    metadata elements, you can switch to the advanced view at any time while
                    editing.</para>

                <para>In the <emphasis role="bold">Advanced View</emphasis>, the ISO profile offers
                    the possibility to visualize and edit the entire metadata structure organized in
                    sections accessible through tabs from the left column. You can use this view to
                    write more advanced metadata descriptions or templates to fit specialized needs.
                        (<xref linkend="advanced_view"/>)</para>

                <figure id="advanced_view">
                    <title>Advanced view</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/advancedView.png" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>The <emphasis role="bold">XML View</emphasis> shows the entire content of the
                    metadata in the original hierarchical structure; different colors allow to
                    distinguish between an element's name and its value. The XML structure is
                    composed of tags and to every tag must correspond a closing tag (<xref
                        linkend="xml_view"/>). The content is entirely contained withing the two,
                    i.e.</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[<gmd:language>
    <gco:CharacterString>eng</gco:CharacterString>
</gmd:language>]]></programlisting>
                <figure id="xml_view">
                    <title>XML view</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/xmlView1.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>Nevertheless, the use of the XML view requires some knowledge of the XML
                    language.</para>

                <para>Both the <emphasis role="bold">Default</emphasis> and the <emphasis
                        role="bold">Advanced Views</emphasis> are composed of
                    <literal>mandatory</literal>, <literal>conditional</literal> and
                        <literal>optional</literal> metadata fields. The meaning of mandatory and
                    optional is fairly intuitive; the mandatory fields are required, like
                        <literal>Title</literal> and <literal>Abstract</literal> for instance,
                    whereas the optional fields can be provided but are not fundamental, depending
                    on the metadata author. The conditional fields may be considered mandatory under
                    certain circumstances: essentially a conditional requirement indicates that the
                    presence of a specified data element is dependent on the value or presence of
                    other data elements in the same section. For instance, the <literal>Individual
                        name</literal> metadata element of the <literal>Point of Contact</literal>,
                    which is a conditional element of the Identification section, becomes mandatory
                    if another element of the same section, <literal>Organization name</literal> or
                        <literal>Position name</literal> is not already defined (<xref
                        linkend="point_of_contact2"/>).</para>
                <figure id="point_of_contact2">
                    <title>Point of Contact</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/PoC_Maint.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>The <emphasis role="bold">mandatory fields</emphasis> as well as those
                        <emphasis role="bold">highly recommended</emphasis> are flagged with
                        <emphasis role="bold">red asterisk</emphasis>
                    <emphasis role="bold">[*]</emphasis>. The standard definition for each field can
                    be read by passing the mouse on the element name.</para>

                <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Default View</emphasis> is the preferred view as it
                    provides a selection of the available metadata elements, facilitating both the
                    user and the editor in reading and editing a metadata record, and at the same
                    time it ensures that a geospatial data can be properly described, through :</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>the minimum set of metadata required to serve the full range of
                            metadata applications (data discovery, determination of data fitness for
                            use, data access, data transfer, and use of digital data);</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>optional metadata elements - to allow for a more extensive standard
                            description of geographic data, if required;</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>a method for extending metadata to fit specialized needs.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Using basic commands of the editor</title>

                <para>Fields are either <emphasis role="bold">free text fields</emphasis> or
                        <emphasis role="bold">drop down lists</emphasis>. Free text means you can
                    type any text into that field. Drop down lists allow you to select only one
                    option from the list. You can add multiple fields of the same kind by clicking
                    on the <emphasis role="bold">[+]</emphasis> symbol next to the element. Every
                    new field that you will add in the advanced view will then be visible in the
                    default view. You can also delete existing fields by clicking on the <emphasis
                        role="bold">[x]</emphasis> symbol next to the element. Clearly, mandatory
                    fields cannot be deleted. One example of the need to add multiple fields can
                    arise if the content of your dataset has some text written in two different
                    languages (<xref linkend="multilingual_data"/>).</para>

                <figure id="multilingual_data">
                    <title>Describing multilingual data</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/multipleElement.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

            </section>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Entering Metadata for your Map</title>

            <para>As we mentioned in the introduction to this guide, GNos provides tools to describe
                any type of geographic data (verctor layers, raster, tables, map services, etc.) as
                well as general document like reports, projects, papers, etc. For the purpose of
                this Quick Start Guide, an example of required and useful metadata elements to
                properly describe a thematic map will be provided hereafter. You should gather as
                much information as possible to identify and understand the map’s resource and
                characteristics you want to describe. Use the default view to start. If necessary,
                you can always switch to advanced view or come back later and edit the record with
                the additonal information collected.</para>

            <section>
                <title>Entering Metadata For Your Map</title>

                <para>Please follow these steps to enter your map's metadata. Note that we will only
                    go through the fields that have been identified as compulsory (i.e. those fields
                    marked with the asterix <emphasis role="bold">[*],</emphasis> mandatory or
                    highly recommended).</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>title</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Title *</emphasis> : Under the <emphasis role="bold"
                        >Identification Info</emphasis> field, give your map a <emphasis role="bold"
                        >name</emphasis>. There will be a default name of your data. Use free text
                    to describe your map here.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>date</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Date *</emphasis> : Indicate the exact <emphasis
                        role="bold">date</emphasis> of <emphasis role="bold">creation</emphasis>,
                        <emphasis role="bold">publication</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold"
                        >revision</emphasis> on your map.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>presentation form</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Presentation Form</emphasis>: Specify the type of
                    presentation, i.e. <emphasis role="bold">digital</emphasis>, <emphasis
                        role="bold">hard copy</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">table</emphasis>,
                    etc.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>abstract</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Abstract *</emphasis> : Enter some description of the map.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>purpose</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Purpose</emphasis>: Enter a short summary of the purposes
                    for your map to be developed.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>status</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Status</emphasis>: Specify the status of your map within
                    the following options: completed, historical archive, obsolete, ongoing,
                    planned, required, under development.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>point of contact</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Point of Contact</emphasis>: Enter all mandatory
                    information and others you have at hand for the contact of the person(s)
                    associated with this resources of the map. Note that some fields are only
                    conditionally mandatory, such as Organization Name if Individual Name and
                    Position are not entered.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>maintenance and update frequency</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Maintenance and update frequency *</emphasis> : Specify
                    the frequency with which you expect to make changes and additions to your map
                    after the initial version is completed. If any changes are scheduled you can
                    leave <literal>As Needed</literal> selected from the drop-down list.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>descriptive keywords</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Descriptive Keywords</emphasis>: Enter keywords that
                    describe your map. Also specify the type of keyword you are entering, i.e.
                    place, theme, etc. Remember that you can add another keyword field if you need
                    to add different types of keywords.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>access constraints</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Access Constraints</emphasis>: Enter an access constraint
                    here, such as a copyright, trademark, etc. to assure the protection of privacy
                    and intellectual property.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>user constraints</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">User Constraints</emphasis>: Enter a user constraint here
                    to assure the protection of privacy and intellectual property.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>other constraints</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Other Constraints *</emphasis> : Enter other constraint
                    here to assure the protection of privacy and intellectual property. Note that
                    this field is conditionally mandatory if Access and Use constraints are not
                    entered.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>spatial representation type</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Spatial representation type</emphasis>: Select, from the
                    drop-down list the method used to spatially represent your data. The options
                    are: vector, grid, text table, stereo model, video.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>scale denominator</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Scale Denominator *</emphasis> : Enter the denominator for
                    an equivalent scale of a hard copy of the map.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>language</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Language *</emphasis> : Select the language used within
                    your map</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>topic category</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Topic category *</emphasis> : Specify the main ISO
                    category/ies through which your map could be classified (see Annex for the
                    complete list of ISO topic categories).</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>temporal extent</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Temporal Extent *</emphasis> : Enter the starting and
                    ending date of the validity period.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>geographic bounding box</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Geographic Bounding Box *</emphasis> : Enter the longitude
                    and latitude for the map or select a region from the predefined drop-down list.
                    Make sure you use degrees for the unit of the geographic coordinates as they are
                    the basis for the geographic searches.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>supplemental information</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Supplemental Information</emphasis>: Enter any other
                    descriptive information about your map that can help the user to better
                    understand its content.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>distribution info</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Distribution Info</emphasis>: Enter information about the
                    distributor and about options for obtaining your map.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>online resource</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Online Resource</emphasis>: Enter information about online
                    resources for the map, such as where a user may download it, etc. This
                    information should include a link, the link type (protocol) and a description of
                    the resource.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>reference system info</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Reference System Info</emphasis>: Enter information about
                    the spatial reference system of your map. The <emphasis role="bold">default view
                        contains</emphasis> one element to provide the <emphasis role="bold"
                        >alphanumeric value</emphasis> identifying the reference system used. GNos
                    uses the <emphasis role="bold">EPSG codes</emphasis> which are numeric codes
                    associated with coordinate system definitions. For instance, EPSG:4326 is
                    Geographic lat-long WGS84, and EPSG:32611 is "UTM zone 11 North, WGS84". Using
                    elements <emphasis role="bold">from the advanced view</emphasis>, you may add
                        <emphasis role="bold">more details</emphasis> on <emphasis role="bold">data
                        projection,</emphasis>
                    <emphasis role="bold">ellipsoid</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold"
                    >datum</emphasis>. Note that if this information is provided, a reference system
                    identifier is not mandatory.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>data quality</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Data Quality</emphasis>: Specify the hierarchal level of
                    the data (<emphasis role="bold">dataset series</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold"
                        >dataset</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">features</emphasis>, <emphasis
                        role="bold">attributes</emphasis>, etc.) and provide a <emphasis role="bold"
                        >general explanation on the production processes</emphasis> (lineage) used
                    for creating the data. The statement element is mandatory if the hierarchical
                    level element is equal to <literal>dataset</literal> or
                    <literal>series</literal>. Detailed information on <emphasis role="bold"
                        >completeness, logical consistency</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold"
                        >positional</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold">thematic</emphasis> and
                        <emphasis role="bold">temporal accuracy</emphasis> can be directly added
                        <emphasis role="bold">into the advanced form</emphasis>.</para>

                <para><indexterm>
                        <primary>metadata author</primary>
                    </indexterm>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Metadata Author *</emphasis> : Provide information about
                    the author of the map, including the person’s name, organization, position, role
                    and any other contact information available.</para>

                <para>After completion of this section, you may select the <emphasis role="bold"
                        >Type</emphasis> of document that you are going to save in the catalogue.
                    You have three options: <emphasis role="bold">Metadata</emphasis>, <emphasis
                        role="bold">Template</emphasis>, <emphasis role="bold"
                    >Sub-template</emphasis>. By default <emphasis role="bold">Metadata</emphasis>
                    is set up.</para>

                <para>When done, you may click <literal>Save</literal> or <literal>Save and
                    Close</literal> to close the editing session.</para>

            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Creating a Thumbnail</title>

                <para>Next, you need to create a graphic overview of your map which will be for a
                    double purpose; as small thumbnail will be displayed in search results and as
                    large thumbnail with much more details, to allow users to properly evaluate the
                    data usefulness. As for the latest, the image that you will use as source should
                    be a significant reproduction of the real dataset, possibly inclusive of the
                    legend.</para>

                <para>To create a thumbnail, go to the editing menu for your map. If you are no
                    longer in editing mode, retrieve the map from one of the search options then
                    click on <literal>Edit</literal>. Then follow these simple steps:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>From the editing menu, click on the <literal>Thumbnails</literal>
                            button on the top or bottom of the page. (<xref
                                linkend="thumbnail_toolbar"/>)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

                <figure id="thumbnail_toolbar">
                    <title>The thumbnail wizard button</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/thumButton.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>You will be taken to the <literal>Thumbnail Management</literal>
                            wizard (<xref linkend="thumbnail_wizard"/>).</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>To create a small or large thumbnail, click on the
                            <literal>Browse</literal> button next to either one. It is recommended
                            that you use 180 pixels for small thumbnails and 800x600 for large
                            thumbnails. Using the ‘Large thumbnail’ option allows you to create both
                            a small and large thumbnail in one go.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>You can use GIF, PNG and JPEG images as input for the
                        thumbnails.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A pop up window will appear allowing you to browse your files on your
                            computer. <literal>Select</literal> the file you wish to create a
                            thumbnail with by double-clicking on it.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Click on <literal>Add</literal>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Your thumbnail will be added and displayed on the following
                        page.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>You can then click on <literal>Back to Editing</literal> and save your
                            record (<xref linkend="completed_thumbnail_wizard"/>).</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

                <figure id="thumbnail_wizard">
                    <title>Thumbnail wizard</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/thumbManag.png" width="10cm" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <figure id="completed_thumbnail_wizard">
                    <title>Completed thumbnail wizard</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/thumbManag2.png" width="10cm" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Linking data for download</title>

                <para>Finally, you can upload the dataset stored on your local computer and then
                    create a link between data and related description. Files in whatever format can
                    be uploaded: doc, PDF, images, vector layers, etc. For the latter the
                    distribution in a compressed file is recommended. You can include the verctor
                    data, the legend, any documentation that can help the interpretation of the
                    data, related reports, detailed descriptions of the data processing, base data
                    used to create the dataset specified and/or other relevant information. Follow
                    these guidelines for uploading datasets:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Make sure the total size of the compressed file is reasonable (less
                            than 50 MB). Should your data be bigger than 50MB, consider a different
                            mechanism to serve this data, e.g. through an FTP or HTTP server and
                            than link the resource through an online resource ‘Web address
                        (URL)’.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>You can create several smaller files when appropriate and upload them
                            sequentially.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>You add the size of the file at the end of the description
                        field.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

                <para>To Upload a Dataset, follow these steps (<xref linkend="online_resource"/>):</para>

                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The <emphasis role="bold">URL</emphasis> field can be left empty when
                            uploading a file. The system will automatically fill this field
                        out;</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Select the correct <emphasis role="bold">protocol</emphasis> to be
                            used. If you do not see the buttons to browse and upload when File for
                            download is selected, save the metadata and return to the upload
                            section. Both buttons should appear;</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Provide a short <emphasis role="bold">description</emphasis> of the
                            data;</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Click the <literal>Browse</literal> button and navigate to the folder
                            where the file to be released is stored. Consider if you want to upload
                            multiple files as one unique zip file or as multiple separate downloads.
                            It is a good idea to add additional documentation with the datasets that
                            provide the user with information related to the data described. Remind:
                            the size of a single file to upload can't exceed 50 Mbytes;</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>Click <literal>Upload</literal> and then
                        <literal>Save</literal>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

                <figure id="online_resource">
                    <title>An online resource</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/uploadData.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Assigning Privileges for a Map</title>

                <para>As an important step of entering metadata to your map, you need to assign
                    privileges for each map. This means that you will identify which work groups
                    have which privileges, i.e. view, download, etc. for your particular map.</para>

                <para>For instance, you can fdefine if the information and related services is
                    visible to all (Internet users) or just to internal users only (Intranet).
                    Privileges are assigned on a per group basis. Depending on the user profile
                    (Guest, Registered User, Editor, Admin etc.) access to these functions may
                    differ on a per user basis.</para>

                <para>To assign privileges for your map, follow these steps:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Find your map by using the search option. Whether you have multiple or
                            single results from the search, on top of the individual record or next
                            to the record you will always see a row of buttons including a
                            Privileges button (<xref linkend="privileges_button"/>).</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

                <figure id="privileges_button">
                    <title>The editing toolbar with <literal>Privileges</literal> button</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/privilegesButton.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Click on the Privileges button. This will take you to a new page. You
                            can assign certain privileges to specific groups by selecting or
                            deselecting them from this page. Simply click on the small box next to
                            the privilege to place or remove a checkmark. <emphasis role="bold"
                                    ><emphasis role="bold">Set Al</emphasis>l</emphasis> and
                                <emphasis role="bold">Clear All</emphasis> buttons allow you to
                            place and remove the checkmarks all at once (<xref
                                linkend="privileges_settings"/>).</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

                <figure id="privileges_settings">
                    <title>Privileges settings</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/privilegesSetting1.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>Below is a brief description for each privilege to help you identify which
                    ones you should assign to which group(s).</para>

                <para><emphasis role="bold">Publish</emphasis>: Users in the specified group/s are
                    able to see the map, i.e. if searching with matching criteria.</para>

                <para><emphasis role="bold">Download</emphasis>: Users in the specified group/s are
                    able to download the map.</para>

                <para><emphasis role="bold">Interactive Map</emphasis>: Users in the specified
                    group/s are able to get an interactive map. <emphasis role="bold">The
                        interactive map</emphasis> has to be created separately using a Web Map
                    Server, which is part of the GeoNetwork opensource application.</para>

                <para><emphasis role="bold">Featured</emphasis>: When selected, the map is placed in
                    the Features Maps of the home page and it appears there randomly.</para>

                <para><emphasis role="bold">Notify</emphasis>: Users in that work group receive
                    notification that the map has been uploaded.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
                <title>Assigning Categories for a Map</title>

                <para>As a final step to entering metadata for a map, you should assign categories
                    for it. The assigned categories will determine the categories the map will
                    display under on the home page. To assign categories for a map, follow these
                    steps:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Find your map by using the search option. Whether you have multiple or
                            single results from your search, on top of the individual record or next
                            to the record, you will always see a row of buttons including a
                                <emphasis role="bold">Categories</emphasis> button.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Click on the <emphasis role="bold">Categories</emphasis> button. This
                            will take you to a new page. You can assign one or multiple categories
                            selecting or deselecting them from this page. Simply click on the small
                            box next to the category to place or remove a checkmark. (<xref
                                linkend="categories_management"/>)</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

                <figure id="categories_management">
                    <title>Category management</title>

                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/categoriesManag.png" width="6cm" align="center"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

            </section>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Uploading a New Record using the XML Metadata Insert Tool</title>

            <para>A more advanced procedure to upload a new metadata record in the GeoNetwork system
                is using an XML document. This procedure is particularly useful for users who
                already have metadata in XML format, for instance created by some GIS application.
                To this regard, it has to be noted that the metadata must be in one of the standards
                used by GeoNetwork: ISO19115, FGDC and Dublin Core.</para>

            <para>To start the metadata uploading process through the <emphasis role="bold">XML
                    Metadata Insert</emphasis> tool, you should log in (see Step. 1. in paragraph
                7.1.1) and select the appropriate option from the Administration page (<xref
                    linkend="administration_panel"/>).</para>

            <figure id="administration_panel">
                <title>Administration panel</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/administration_panel.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>The main part of the page <emphasis role="bold">Import XML Formatted
                Metadata</emphasis> that is displayed (<xref linkend="xml_import"/>) is the
                    <emphasis role="bold">Metadata</emphasis> text area, where the user can paste
                the XML metadata to import. Below this, there is the <emphasis role="bold"
                >Type</emphasis> choise, which allows you select the type of record that you are
                going to create (Metadata, Template and Subtemplate). Then you can apply a
                stylesheet to convert your metadata input from ArcCatalog8 to ISO1915 or from
                ISO19115 to ISO19139, if required. Otherwise you can just leave
                <replaceable>none</replaceable> selected. The <emphasis role="bold">Destination
                    schema</emphasis> list provides you with four options to choose the final
                standard layout for your metadata (ISO19115, ISO19139, FDGDC and Dublin Core).
                Finally you should select the <emphasis role="bold">Group</emphasis> as main group
                in charge of the metadata and the <emphasis role="bold">Category</emphasis> that you
                want to assign to your metadata. By clicking the <emphasis role="bold"
                >Insert</emphasis> button the metadata is imported into the system; please note that
                all links to external files, for istance to thumbnails or data for download, have to
                be removed from the metadata input, to avoid any conflict within the data
                repository.</para>

            <figure id="xml_import">
                <title>XML metadata import tool</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/xmlImporTool.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">
                    <emphasis/>
                </emphasis>
            </para>

            <para>If your metadata is already in ISO19115 format, the main actions to be performed
                are the following (<xref linkend="xml_import_2"/>):</para>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Paste the XML file that contains the metadata information in the <emphasis
                            role="bold">Metadata</emphasis> text area;</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Select Metadata as <emphasis role="bold">type</emphasis> of record that
                        you are going to create</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Select the metadata schema ISO19139 that will be the final <emphasis
                            role="bold">destination schema</emphasis>;</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Select the <emphasis role="bold">validate</emphasis> check box if you want
                        your metadata to be validated according to the related schema.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Select the <emphasis role="bold">group</emphasis> in charge of the
                        metadata from the drop down list;</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Select <emphasis role="bold">Maps and Graphics</emphasis> from the list of
                        categories;</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>Click the <emphasis role="bold">Insert</emphasis> button and the metadata
                        will be imported into the system.</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>

            <figure id="xml_import_2">
                <title>XML metadata import 2</title>

                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/xmlImporTool2.png" width="11cm" align="center"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
