<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
    <chapter id="docbook_guidelines_chapter1">
        <title>Writing GeoNetwork opensource documentation</title>
        <section>
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <para> The GeoNetwork documentation is written in <ulink url="http://www.docbook.org"
                    >DocBook</ulink> format. DocBook is a collection of standards and tools for
                technical publishing. DocBook was originally created by a consortium of software
                companies as a standard for computer documentation. But the basic “book” features of
                DocBook can be used for other kinds of content, so it has been adapted to many
                purposes. DocBook is an XML format. An example of the source of Chapter 2 of this
                document can be seen in Part II of this document.</para>
            <para>Using DocBook as the documentation format has some big advantages. The format
                allows us to</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>integrate new documentation relatively easy</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>keep content separate from layout/formatting</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>generate HTML and PDF documents (and possibly others) from one set of
                        source documents</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>stay away from complex and/or proprietary document formats</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>maintain versions of the documentation</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>integrate the build process of the output documents in the standard
                        software compilation process based on 
                            <ulink url="http://ant.apache.org">Ant</ulink>
                        </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>The Document is split up into Parts that serve different user groups. These groups
                are the general visitor, spatial data and information managers, system
                administrators, system integrators and software developers.</para>
            <para>Each Part is split up in Chapters. Chapters are saved as separate files. A prefix
                is added to the filenames and the filename reflects the Chapter title. Chapters have
                sections that cover a limited topic.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Writing DocBook documentation</title>
            <para>The documentation should be written using only a limited number of the available
                DocBook <code><![CDATA[<elements>]]></code>. A brief overview of the most commonly
                used elements is provided in the next chapter.</para>
            <para>The easiest way to write DocBook XML documents is to use an XML editor. XML
                editors will normally suggest what elements you can use, close elements for you and
                give warnings when you make errors.</para>
            <para>Popular XML editors are available as plugins to <ulink
                    url="http://www.eclipse.org">Eclipse</ulink>, see the XML section on the <ulink
                    url="http://www.eclipseplugincentral.com/">Eclipse Plugin Central</ulink>.</para>
            <para>You can also use text editors to edit DocBook files.</para>
            <warning>
                <para>Be careful that the documents you write are well formed and valid DocBook
                XML.</para>
            </warning>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Generating the documentation in HTML and PDF</title>
            <para>To generate the final documentation in HTML or PDF, <literal>Ant</literal> is
                required to be installed on your computer.</para>
            <para>Open a Terminal window and <literal>cd</literal> (change directory) into the
                    <filename>docs</filename> folder. Type <code>ant</code> and hit Return. All the
                documentation should now be compiled and a new Manual.pdf file and new content in
                the HTML folder should be generated.</para>
            <para>To only generate the PDF document you can run <userinput>ant pdf</userinput>, 
                while you can run <code>ant html</code> to only generate the HTML files. 
                To generate the Javadoc source code documentation run <code>ant javadoc</code>.</para>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</book>
